Register of the Józef Frejlich Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Józef Frejlich collection,
1891-1968
68023
Frejlich, Józef, collector
81 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (33.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, bulletins, press releases, serial issues, pamphlets, and other printed matter, relating to Polish history and politics, socialism in Poland, Poland during World War II, the Yalta Conference, Poles in the United States and Canada, anti-communist movements, and the Russian Orthodox Church. Includes some correspondence of J. Frejlich and newspaper articles written by him.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (84 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
Jozef Frejlich, collector, historian, and economist was able to leave Warsaw in 1940 as a result of the efforts of his party colleagues, who were members of the government-in-exile in London. As an active and well-known member of the Polish Socialist Party (Polska Partia Socjalistyczna), he was smuggled through many borders to Portugal where, in 1942, he received a visa to the United States. Upon his arrival in New York the following year, he was hired by the Polish Consulate to oversee the government's financial operations. Later he was transferred to the German Department of the Polish Information Center, and remained there until its closing in 1945. His main assignment was to stay in touch with German and Jewish-Americans circles, which were of particular interest to the Polish diplomatic services. His own political views also brought him closer to the activities of the socialist groups, but he soon found himself in conflict with those who manifested their support for the Soviet Union.
This collection reflects Frejlich's professional activities, as it contains mainly printed materials such as press clippings, which he analyzed as a press reviewer. However, he continued this work long after the closing of the government's operations. A large portion of those press clippings originated from the émigré newspapers published in the United States, a majority of which from the German press, which, to a large extent, reflected the opinions not of the German minority but of the German speaking Jewish immigrants. There are also some German language titles printed in Switzerland, a country with good insights into the political developments on the European continent.
Frejlich's political association with the socialist movement both in Poland and in the United States is reflected in a large set of documents left for him in the last will of Wladyslaw Fischler, who was active in the Zwiazek Socjalistow Polskich w Stanach Zjednoczonych. They illustrate the liveliness of political life among Polish immigrant workers in the United States.
The collection also includes Frejlich's articles written for numerous Polish-American journals, as well as rare documents, periodicals, and monographs supplementing other collections in the Hoover Archives on World War II, socialism, and Poles in the United States and Europe, particularly the records of the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji and of the Polish Information Center.
The papers were part of a larger shipment delivered to the Hoover Archives in 1969. Besides materials that originated in the Polish Information Center, the shipment contained several thousand books deposited at the Hoover Library. Because of Frejlich's interest in the history of socialism, he was offered the position of honorary curator of the Polish socialist collection; unfortunately, his advanced age didn't allow him to accept that offer.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Yalta Conference (1945); Poles--Canada.; Poles--United States.; Socialism--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Canada.; Poland.; Poland--History.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); United States.; Poland--Politics and government.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Anti-communist movements.; Communism.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1940-1967. (Box 1-4)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Writings, 1943-1958. (Box 4-9)
  Newspaper articles, arranged chronologically, and poems
- Subject File, 1893-1966. (Box 9-31)
  Clippings, correspondence, brochures, bulletins, reports, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Clippings, 1940-1948. (Box 32-66)
  Clippings arranged chronologically and therein alphabetically by the language in which they were published
- Printed Matter, 1920-1961. (Box 67-81)
  Bulletins, cartoons, flyers, and maps, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes some newspapers and clippings
- Oversize Material, 1946-1955. (Box Map case)
  French anti-communist posters and proclamations
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1940-1967 (Box 1)
  - General
    - General
      - General, 1940-1942 (Folder 1: 1)
      - Family and friends
        - 1940-1941 (Folder 1: 2)
        - 1946-1966 (Folder 1: 3)
    - 1941-1942. (Folder 1: 4)
      Includes letters from the Warsaw Ghetto
    - 1942 (Folder 1: 5)
    - 1943 (Folder 1: 6)
    - 1944 (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1945 (Folder 1: 8)
    - 1946 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1947 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1950 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1951 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1952 (Folder 1: 13)
    - 1953 (Folder 1: 14)
    - 1954 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 1955 (Folder 1: 16)
    - 1956 (Folder 1: 17)
    - 1957 (Folder 1: 18)
    - 1958 (Folder 1: 19)
    - 1959 (Folder 1: 20)
    - 1960 (Folder 1: 21)
    - 1961 (Folder 1: 22)
    - 1962 (Folder 1: 23)
    - 1963 (Folder 1: 24)
    - 1964 (Folder 1: 25)
    - 1965 (Folder 1: 26)
    - 1966 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Alizewski, J., 1966. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Correspondence related to millennium celebrations
  - Arciszewska, Melania
    - 1956-1959 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1960-1966 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Arciszewski, Tomasz
    - 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 4)
    - 1946 (Folder 2: 5)
    - 1947 (Folder 2: 6)
    - 1948 (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1949 (Folder 2: 8)
    - 1950 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Arquivo Historico Militar Lisbon, 1949 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Baginski, Kazimierz
    - 1953-1964 (Folder 2: 11)
    - 1965-1966 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Biblioteka Narodowa, 1963-1967 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Ciolkosz, Adam
    - 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 14)
    - 1942 (Folder 2: 15)
    - 1943-1944 (Folder 2: 16)
    - 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 17)
    - 1952-1959 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Czaykowski, W., 1956-1959 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Czerwinscy, W. Z., 1940 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Dallin, David, J., 1943-1960 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Dehnel, Jan, 1966 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Drucki-Lubecki, 1952-1960 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Fryling, Jan, 1966 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Gantz, A., 1942-1943 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Gierszynski, Witold, 1943 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Gosta, John, 1963 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Haiman, Mieczyslaw, 1942 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Honigwill, Ludwik
    - 1943-1948 (Folder 2: 29)
    - 1950 (Folder 2: 30)
    - 1951 (Folder 2: 31)
    - 1952 (Folder 2: 32)
    - 1953 (Folder 2: 33)
    - 1954 (Folder 2: 34)
    - 1955 (Folder 2: 35)
    - 1956 (Folder 2: 36)
    - 1957 (Folder 2: 37)
    - 1958 (Folder 2: 38)
    - 1959 (Folder 2: 39)
    - 1960-1961 (Folder 2: 40)
  - Kraczkiewicz, Adam, 1966 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Kruszka, Jozef, 1906 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Lechon, Jan, 1944 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Lerski, Jerzy, 1955-1957 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Librach, Jan, 1942 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Lubecki, Jan
    - 1951-1956 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 1960-1961 (Folder 3: 7)
    - 1963-1966 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Meyer, Alfred G., 1956 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Minc, A., 1956-1957 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Minkowski, Mieczyslaw, 1940-1966 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris, 1940-1958 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Olszewski, J., 1964-1966 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Pehr, Otto
    - 1950-1953 (Folder 3: 14)
    - 1954-1955 (Folder 3: 15)
    - 1956-1957 (Folder 3: 16)
    - 1958-1960 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Polski Instytut Naukowy w Ameryce, 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Possony, Stefan, 1957 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Przegalinski, Boleslaw
    - 1954 (Folder 3: 20)
    - 1955 (Folder 3: 21)
    - 1956 (Folder 3: 22)
    - 1957 (Folder 3: 23)
    - 1958 (Folder 3: 24)
    - 1959 (Folder 3: 25)
    - 1960-1961 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Rogozinska, Irena, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Szterm, Edward, 1941 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Waghalter, Ignatz (Icek), 1943-1945 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Waghalter-Kronberger, Jolanta (Yolanda), 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Werenych, Henryk, 1962-1964 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Wittlin, Jozef, 1941 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Wlodarczyk, J. D.
    - 1944-1951 (Folder 4: 7)
    - 1952-1956 (Folder 4: 8)
    - 1957-1959 (Folder 4: 9)
    - 1960-1966 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Wszelaki, Jan, 1961 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Zenzinov, V., 1943 (Folder 4: 12)
- WRITINGS, 1943-1958
  - Newspaper articles
    - 1943 (Folder 4: 13-15)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    - 1945 (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1945-1946 (Folder 5: 4)
    - 1946 (Folder 5: 5)
    - 1948-1954 (Folder 5: 6)
    - 1950 (Box 6)
      - Typescripts (Folder 6: 1)
      - Printed copies (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1951
      - Typescripts (Folder 6: 3)
      - Printed copies (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1952 (Box 7)
      - Typescripts (Folder 7: 1)
      - Printed copies (Folder 7: 2)
    - 1953
      - Typescripts (Folder 7: 3)
      - Printed copies (Folder 7: 4)
    - 1954
      - Typescripts (Folder 7: 5)
      - Printed copies (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1955
      - Typescripts (Folder 8: 2)
      - Printed copies (Folder 8: 3)
    - 1956
      - Typescripts (Folder 8: 4)
      - Printed copies (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - 1957
      - Typescripts (Folder 9: 2)
      - Printed copies (Folder 9: 3)
    - 1958
      - Typescripts (Folder 9: 4)
      - Printed copies (Folder 9: 5)
  - Poems, 1942-1956 (Folder 9: 6)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1893-1966
  - General
    - 1942 (Folder 9: 7)
    - 1943 (Folder 9: 8)
    - 1944
      - General (Folder 9: 9)
      - Printed matter (Folder 9: 10)
  - Africa, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - American Labor Conference on International Affairs, 1946-1956 (Folder 10: 2)
  - American Political Science Association - Annual meeting, 1961 (Folder 10: 3)
  - American Relief for Poland, 1957-1958 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Anders, Wladyslaw
    - General, 1956 (Folder 10: 5)
    - Court case against Narodowiec, 1960 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Artists - Poles, 1890-1910 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Asia
    - 1949 (Folder 10: 8)
    - 1954 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Assembly of Captive European Nations, 1961-1965 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Austria
    - 1944 (Folder 10: 11)
    - 1966 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Austrian-Americans, 1942-1944 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve Systems (U.S.), 1943 (Folder 10: 14)
  - Bor-Komorowski, Tadeusz, 1946 (Folder 10: 15)
  - Catholic Church - Poland
    - Church-state relations, 1964 (Folder 10: 16)
    - Polish-American protest, 1945 (Folder 10: 17)
    - Polish Embassy to the Vatican, 1958-1959 (Folder 10: 18)
  - China - Relations - Russia, 1943 (Folder 10: 19)
    (in Polish)
  - Christian Democratic Union of Central Europe - Congress, 1953 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Churchill, Winston
    - 1950 (Folder 11: 2)
    - 1951 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Ciechanowski, Jan, 1947 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Cwiklinski, Jan R. - Testimony, U.S. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws, 1954 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Cyprus, 1964 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Dmowski, Roman, 1964 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Dziennik Polski, 1965 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Egzekutywa Zjednoczenia Narodowego, 1956 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Emigration and immigration law - United States, 1955 (Folder 11: 10)
  - Falkenhausen, Gothrad, F., 1948 (Folder 11: 11)
  - Fischler, Wladyslaw (Fiszler)., See also Zwiazek Socjalistow Polskich w Stanach Zjednoczonych
    - General (Folder 11: 12)
    - Clippings
      - 1893 (Folder 11: 13)
      - 1896 (Folder 11: 14)
      - 1906 (Folder 11: 15)
      - 1906-1935 (Box-folder 12: 1)
      - 1891-1902, 1915 (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1908-1912, 1931-1939 (Folder 12: 3)
      - 1934-1939 (Folder 12: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1898 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Fliers (Folder 12: 6)
    - Membership cards (Folder 12: 7)
  - Frejlich, Helena, 1933-1952 (Folder 12: 8)
  - Friedel, F. T.
    - Jezuici i Ich Lobuzerska Robota, n.d. (Folder 12: 9)
    - Konkordat i Walka Przeciw Jego Przyjeciu, n.d. (Folder 12: 10)
    - Satyryk
      - 1943 (Folder 12: 11)
      - 1944 (Folder 12: 12)
  - Gawlina, Jozef, Archbishop, 1955 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - German Americans, 1942-1945 (Folder 13: 2)
  - Germans - Great Britain, 1943-1945 (Folder 13: 3)
  - Germany, 1954 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Great Britain, 1913-1941 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Heilperin, Michal, n.d. (Folder 13: 6)
  - Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) - Poland (Folder 13: 7)
  - Honigwill, Ludwik, 1946 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Inheritance and succession - Poland, 1942-1943 (Folder 13: 9)
  - International Peasant Union, 1948
    - General (Folder 13: 10)
    - Program (Folder 13: 11)
    - United Nations General Assembly (Folder 13: 12)
  - International Trade Organization, 1947 (Folder 13: 13)
  - Israel, 1966 (Folder 13: 14)
  - Jews., See also National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1944
    - General (Folder 13: 15)
    - Germany (Folder 13: 16)
    - Palestine, 1942 (Folder 13: 17)
    - Poland
      - General (Folder 13: 18)
      - Kielce, 1946 (Folder 13: 19)
    - United States, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Kara, Stanislaw, 1941 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940
    - General, 1943 (Folder 14: 3)
    - Voice of America radio reports., See also United States. Congress. House. Select Committee to Conduct an Investigation and Study of the Facts, Evidence, and Circumstances on the Katyn Forest Massacre, 1952 (Folder 14: 4)
  - Komitet Narodowy Amerykanow Polskiego Pochodzenia, 1942 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Korfanty, Wojciech, 1956 (Folder 14: 6)
  - Krivitsky, Walter, 1966 (Folder 14: 7)
  - Lange, Oskar
    - 1943 (Folder 14: 8)
    - 1944 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Lee, Algernoon, 1943 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Lieberman, Herman - Defamation case, 1942 (Folder 14: 11)
  - Lussa, Emilio, 1941 (Folder 14: 12)
  - Malinowski, Wladyslaw, 1942 (Folder 14: 13)
  - Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw
    - Interview, 1947 (Folder 14: 14)
    - Clippings about memoirs, 1948 (Folder 14: 15)
  - Minorities - Soviet Union, 1952 (Folder 14: 16)
  - Monetary and Economic Conference (1952: Moscow) (Folder 14: 17)
  - National Committee for a Free Europe. Research and Information Center, 1950 (Folder 14: 18)
  - National Committee of Americans of Polish Descent, 1957 (Folder 14: 19)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1944 (Folder 14: 20)
  - O'Konski, Alvin E., 1946 (Folder 14: 21)
  - Ogólny Zydowski Zwiazek Robotniczy "Bund" w Polsce. Amerykanska Reprezentacja, 1897-1957 (Folder 14: 22)
  - Pajak, Antoni, 1956 (Folder 14: 22)
  - Pankiewicz, Michal
    - 1942 (Folder 14: 23)
    - 1943 (Folder 14: 24)
  - Poland (Box 15)
    - General
      - General (Folder 15: 1)
      - Biographies of political, military, and social 20th century personalities (Folder 15: 2)
      - Reports on Red Army conduct on the Polish territory, 1944 August-November (Folder 15: 3)
      - Boundaries
      - East
        - General (Folder 15: 4)
        - Curzon Line, 1945 (Folder 15: 5)
      - West - Oder-Neisse, 1952 (Folder 15: 6)
    - Constitution, 1935. (Folder 15: 7)
      English translation
    - Foreign relations
      - Soviet Union
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 15: 8)
        - 1944 (Folder 15: 9)
        - 1945 (Folder 15: 10)
      - United States - Economic negotiations, 1957 (Folder 15: 11)
    - History - Uprising, 1956 (Folder 15: 12)
    - Politics and government
      - General, 1942-1953 (Folder 15: 13)
      - Peace treaty with Germany, 1947 (Folder 15: 14)
      - Recognition, 1945 (Folder 15: 15)
    - Sovietization of Polish system in the 1950s (Folder 15: 16)
  - Poland. Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej, 1943 (Folder 15: 17)
  - Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych. (Folder 15: 18)
    Report on German occupation of Poland, 1939-1941
  - Poland. Najwyzsza Izba Kontroli, 1943 (Folder 15: 19)
  - Poland. Najwyzsza Izba Kontroli, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
  - Poland. Prezydium Rady Ministrow, 1952-1954 (Folder 16: 3)
  - Poland. Sekretariat Generalny Skarbu Jednosci, 1954 (Folder 16: 4)
  - Poland. Skarb Narodowy, 1949-1953 (Folder 16: 5)
  - Poles - Great Britain, 1960 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Polish American Congress
    - 1944 (Folder 16: 7-10)
    - 1945 (Folder 16: 11)
    - 1946 (Folder 16: 12)
    - 1947 (Folder 16: 13)
    - 1948 (Folder 16: 14)
    - 1950 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - 1951 (Folder 17: 2)
    - 1952 (Folder 17: 3-4)
    - 1955 (Folder 17: 5)
    - 1956
      - General (Folder 17: 6)
      - Congress (Folder 17: 7)
  - Polish Americans, 1944-1956 (Folder 17: 8-9)
  - Polish Information Center (Box 18)
    - Courier shipments. Lists, 1945 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Grupa Dyskusyjna. Discussion transcripts
      - 1941 (Folder 18: 2)
      - 1942 (Folder 18: 3)
  - Poland Fights - Budget (Folder 18: 4)
  - Polish Library, Paris, 1956 (Folder 18: 5)
  - Polish University College, London. Department of Economics and Commerce, 1950-1951 (Folder 18: 6)
  - Politicians - United States, 1900-1945 (Folder 18: 7)
  - Polska Partia Komunistyczna, n.d. (Folder 18: 8)
  - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 18: 9)
    - 1940 (Folder 18: 10)
    - 1942 (Folder 18: 11)
    - 1943 (Folder 18: 12)
    - 1945-1946 (Folder 18: 13)
    - 1947 (Folder 18: 14)
    - 1948 (Folder 18: 15)
    - 1949-1958 (Folder 18: 16)
    - 1960-1962 (Folder 18: 17)
  - Polska Robotnicza Kasa Pomocy, 1910-1960 (Folder 18: 18)
  - Polskie Stronnictwo Demokratyczne, 1944 (Folder 18: 19)
  - Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe
    - General
      - General
        - 1945-1947 (Folder 18: 20)
        - 1948 (Folder 18: 21)
        - 1952 (Box-folder 19: 1)
        - 1953 (Folder 19: 2)
        - 1954 (Folder 19: 3)
        - 1955 (Folder 19: 4)
        - 1957 (Folder 19: 5)
      - Printed matter (Folder 19: 6)
    - Baginski, Kazimierz (Folder 19: 7)
    - Elections, 1947
      - Part 1 (Folder 19: 8)
      - Part 2 (Folder 19: 9)
    - Naczelny Komitet Wykonawczy - Political line, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Rada Polonii Amerykanskiej. Report of the president, 1959 (Folder 20: 2)
  - Rada Zjednoczenia Narodowego (Council of National Unity), 1944 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1950-1952 (Folder 20: 4)
  - Reconstruction (1939-1951)
    - General. Bibliography, 1944 (Folder 20: 5)
    - Central Europe, 1943 (Folder 20: 6)
    - Renner, G. T., 1942 (Folder 20: 7)
  - Refugees - Poland. Survey of the Polish refugee and immigrant centers in Europe, 1947-1955., See also World War, 1939-1945 (Folder 20: 8)
  - Relief Society for Poles, 1949 (Folder 20: 9)
  - Russia
    - Foreign relations., See China - Relations - Russia
    - Politics and government, 1900-1918 (Folder 20: 10)
  - Russian Orthodox Church
    - General (Folder 20: 11)
    - Congress, 1948 (Folder 20: 12)
  - Russian Research Center, Harvard University. Catalog, 1951 (Folder 20: 13)
  - Schumacher, Kurt. Obituary, 1952 (Folder 20: 14)
  - Schuman Plan, 1952 (Folder 20: 15)
  - Schwarzbart, I., 1943 (Folder 20: 16)
  - Sharp, Samuel L., 1953-1954 (Folder 20: 17)
  - Siekanowicz, Peter - Administration of Justice (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - Sikorski, Wladyslaw, 1942 (Folder 21: 2)
  - Slovak-Americans (Folder 21: 3)
  - Smith, Walter Bedell. Clippings about memoirs, 1949 (Folder 21: 4)
  - Socialism
    - General (Folder 21: 5)
    - Great Britain. Bulletin officiel du Parti Socialiste Polonais
      - 1895 (Folder 21: 6)
      - 1896 (Folder 21: 7)
      - 1897 (Folder 21: 8)
      - 1898 (Folder 21: 9)
    - Poland
      - General (Folder 21: 10)
      - Bulletins (Folder 21: 11)
    - United States
      - General
        - Booklets (Folder 21: 12)
        - Bulletins (Box-folder 22: 1)
        - Correspondence (Folder 22: 2)
        - Flyers (Folder 22: 3-5)
      - Ethnic minorities
        - Germans (Folder 22: 6)
        - Poles
          - Bulletins (Folder 22: 7)
          - Flyers (Folder 22: 8)
          - Flyers (Box-folder 23: 1-2)
          - List of organizations and their divisions, ca. 1900-1920 (Folder 23: 3)
  - Socjalistyczna Partia Robotnicza Stanow Zjednoczonych Polnocnej Ameryki. Constitution, 1896 (Folder 23: 4)
  - Soviet Union
    - General
      - 1949 (Folder 23: 5)
      - 1954 (Folder 23: 6)
    - Foreign relations
      - Asia, 1931-1942 (Folder 23: 7)
      - Poland, 1944 (Folder 23: 8)
    - Presence in Eastern Europe, 1947-1952 (Folder 23: 9)
  - Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantow w Stanach Zjednoczonych, 1953-1955 (Folder 23: 10)
  - Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantow w Wielkiej Brytanii
    - General, 1949-1951 (Folder 23: 11)
    - Congress, 1950 (Box-folder 24: 1-2)
  - Stowarzyszenie Prawnikow Polskich w Stanach Zjednoczonych, 1941 (Folder 24: 3)
  - Szymczak, Matt S.
    - General, 1942-1961 (Folder 24: 4)
    - Speeches, 1936-1948 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Ukrainian Americans, 1944 (Folder 24: 6)
  - United Nations, 1943-1958 (Folder 24: 7)
  - United States
    - General, 1943-1944 (Folder 24: 8)
    - Foreign relations
      - Soviet Union, 1960 (Folder 24: 9)
      - Third world countries, 1953 (Folder 24: 10)
  - United States Congress. House of Representatives. Select Committee on the Katyn Forest Massacre - Hearings transcripts (Box 25)
    - General
      - Part 1 (Folder 25: 1)
      - Part 2 (Folder 25: 2)
      - Part 3 (Folder 25: 3)
      - Part 5 (Folder 25: 4)
      - Part 6 (Folder 25: 5)
      - Part 7 (Folder 25: 6)
      - Final report (Folder 25: 7)
    - Voice of America report (Folder 25: 8)
  - Warsaw (Poland) - History - Uprising, 1944 (Folder 25: 9)
  - Warsaw (Poland) - History - Warsaw Ghetto Uprising, 1943 (Folder 25: 10)
  - Winiewicz, Jozef, 1939 (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - Wlodarczyk, Joseph
    - Clippings, 1927-1945 (Folder 26: 2)
    - Printed matter, 1908-1952 (Folder 26: 3)
    - Speeches, 1945 (Folder 26: 4)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - Civilian relief, 1943 (Folder 26: 5)
    - Deportations from Poland
      - General
        - 1939-1941 (Folder 26: 6)
        - 1944-1945 (Folder 26: 7)
      - Clothing for deportees, 1942 (Folder 26: 8)
    - Refugees - Poland
      - Africa (Folder 26: 9)
      - Argentina (Folder 26: 10)
      - Austria (Folder 26: 11)
      - Belgium (Folder 26: 12)
      - Germany
        - General (Folder 26: 13)
        - Literary works (Folder 26: 14)
      - Great Britain (Folder 26: 15)
      - Italy (Folder 26: 16)
  - Yalta Conference (1945)
    - Official record, 1945 (Folder 26: 17)
    - Political parties
      - Democrats, 1952 (Folder 26: 18)
      - Republicans, 1955 (Folder 26: 19)
  - Zaleski, W. - Ruch tysiaclecia, 1953 (Box-folder 27: 1)
  - Zielinski, Henryk - Post-war planning, 1942 (Folder 27: 2)
  - Zwiazek Narodowy Polski. Clippings, 1958-1959 (Folder 27: 3)
  - Zwiazek Obrony Niepodleglosci Polski, 1945-1948
    - General
      - General (Folder 27: 4)
      - Communiqué 1945-1946 (Folder 27: 5)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1948 (Folder 27: 6)
    - Paris Conference, 1946 (Folder 27: 7)
  - Zwiazek Socjalistow Polskich w Stanach Zjednoczonych., See also Fischler, Wladyslaw
    - Clippings
      - 1901 (Folder 27: 8)
      - 1901-1903 (Folder 27: 9)
      - 1902-1903 (Box-folder 28: 1)
      - 1904 (Folder 28: 2)
      - 1904-1905 (Folder 28: 3)
      - 1905
        - February-September (Folder 28: 4)